Guide to the Robert LaVigne papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Robert LaVigne Papers,
1954-1969.
LaVigne, Robert, 1928-
3 linear ft. (2 document boxes & 1 map case drawer)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0747
4079553
The papers of artist and Beat Generation figure Robert LaVigne. The collection contains correspondence, artwork, and event invitations.
Biographical Note
Robert LaVigne is a painter, illustrator, and theatrical set designer associated with the Beat Generation and poets of the San Francisco Renaissance.
LaVigne was born in St. Maries Idaho in 1928, but moved to San Francisco in 1951. There he became associated with a number of poets and counter-culture figures centered around the North Beach neighborhood of San Francisco, including Michael McClure, Philip Whalen, and Peter Orlovsky.
LaVigne met Orlovsky in a coffee shop in San Francisco and almost immediately took the younger man as his muse, bringing him to live with him as a model and lover. It was at LaVigne's studio that Allen Ginsberg first met and subsequently fell in love with Peter Orlovksy-- first his image in a large, nude portrait that LaVigne had painted, and then with the young man himself.
In San Francisco LaVigne worked as a painter, illustrator and a set designer for the San Francisco Actors Workshop. He also worked as the Art Director of the Auerhahn Press-- a small fine press that focused on the work of the San Francisco Renaissance poets.
Like many members of the Beat Generation, LaVigne moved between coasts, leaving San Francisco for New York in the 1960s. While working in New York he was a pioneer of the painting style known as psychedelic painting, and continued to work in the theater, earning an Obie award for Best Design for his work on A Midsummer Nights Dream and Endicott and the Red Cross.
LaVigne eventually returned to the west coast, moving to Seattle in the early 1980s.
Scope and Content
The Robert LaVigne Papers include correspondence, artwork, manuscripts, and event announcements related to the work of Robert LaVigne and his group of friends.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in III series
Series I. Correspondence and Manuscripts, 1954-1969
Series II. Artwork, 1956-1965
Series III. Exhibition and Event Announcements, 1958-1964
Subjects
Cassady, Neal.; Connor, Bruce.; Corso, Gregory.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Kerouac, Jack, 1922-1969.; Lamantia, Philip, 1927-2005.; LaVigne, Robert, 1928-; McClure, Michael.; Malanga, Gerard.; Olson, Charles, 1910-1970.; Orlovsky, Peter, 1933-; Plymell, Charles.; Whalen, Philip.; Wieners, John, 1934-2002.; American poetry--20th century.; Art.; Authors, American--20th century.; Avant-garde art.; Beat generation.; Poets, American--20th century.; Theater.; Bohemianism--United States.; Announcements.; Book covers.; Catalogs.; Costume design drawings.; Drawings.; Poems.; Portraits.; Prefaces.; Set design drawings.; Sketches.; Watercolor drawings.; Woodcuts.; Artists.; Authors.; Designers.; Illustrators.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1985 M-1985 Papers Purchase
- Series I: Correspondence and Manuscripts,1954-1969
  This series is comprised of letters and manuscripts composed by Robert LaVigne and his friends and associates. Because so many of LaVigne's friends were writers, there is a significant set of poetry manuscripts included on this series that were given to or reviewed by LaVigne.
  - Aldan, Daisy-- "Christmas" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brukenfield, Richard to Gregory Corso, 13 November 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cassady Neal to LaVigne, 24 March 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Corso, Gregory to LaVigne, undated and 1957-1958 (4 letters) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dine, Jim to John Hancock, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Doyle, Kirby and Lew Welch to LaVigne, 1961 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ginsberg, Allen
    - to LaVigne, undated and 1960-1968 (4 letters) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Empty Mirror Typescript, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (with notes and corrections by LaVigne)
    - Poems, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (including some omitted from Empty Mirror and "Record of Dream 6 June 1955")
    - Preface to LaVigne's LION Exhibition, 1958 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Recipe for Spaghetti with Clam Sauce, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ginsberg, Louis to LaVigne, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lamantia, Philip
    - to LaVigne, undated and 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Blue Grace", undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      (poem, with corrections)
    - Draft of Text for Poster Advertising a Poetry Reading, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - LaVigne, Robert
    - To Andreas Brown, 1969 (3 letters) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Dangerous Garden of Robert LaVigne (Box 1, Folder 17)
      (poems by a number of individuals, including Allen Ginsberg, inspired by LaVigne's art)
    - Prologue to Endicott and the Red Cross (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - McClure, Michael
    - To LaVigne, undated (5 letters) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "Introduction to the Poems of John Wieners," 1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      (two drafts)
    - Poems, undated and 1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Malanga, Gerard
    - To Lavigne, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Poems (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Orlovsky, Peter to LaVigne, 1954-1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Plymell, Charles-- Poems, undated and 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth-- Libretto for the ballet Original Sin, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    (ballet commissioned by the San Francisco Ballet- file contains the first act)
  - Sanders, Ed-- [Poem on the Death of His Mother], 1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Snow, John to Allen Ginsberg, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Whalen, Philip
    - To LaVigne, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Against the Magic War: An Open Letter to Robert Duncan," 1957 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Wieners, John
    - To LaVigne, undated and 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Poems, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series II: Artwork, 1956-1965
  This series includes paintings, sketches, prints, and paintings done by LaVigne, as well as artwork created by his friends. This series includes some of LaVigne's artwork, but also some of his design work including book cover designs and four costume designs for a performance of Picasso's Desire Caught by the Tail.
  - Corso, Gregory
    - Ink Sketches (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kerouac, Jack
    - Sketches, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ginsberg, Allen-- sketches, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    (one watercolor sketch)
  - LaVigne, Robert
    - Cover Designs for Human Universe by Charles Olsen, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Cover Design for The Hotel Wentley Poems by John Wieners, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Costume Designs for Desire Caught by the Taik
      - Big Foot. Arlequino, Handyman, 1967 (Folder 14-E-6)
      - Naked. A Skinny Anguish of Red Inner Tube, 1967 (Folder 14-E-6)
      - Silence, 1967 (Folder 14-E-6)
      - Tart, 1967 (Folder 14-E-6)
    - Preliminary Sketches of the Album Cover of Allen Ginsberg Reads From Howl and Kadish (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Sketches, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Sketches of Peter Orlovsky, 1954 April- June (Folder 14-E-6)
    - Watercolor portrait of Allen Ginsberg, 1971 (Folder 14-E-6)
    - Oversized Painting (Box 13: D/E)
    - Woodblock Print- "A Strange New Cottage in Berkeley," 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - McClure, Michael
    - Sketches, undated and 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Sketches and Auerhaun Press Broadsides (Folder 14-E-6)
  - Whalen, Philip-- Watercolors, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series III: Exhibition and Event Announcements, 1958-1964
  The Exhibition and Event Announcements series is comprised of notices of gallery events, art openings, and poetry readings, as well as publication catalogs and announcements from small, independent presses and publishers.
  - Auerhahn Press, undated and 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Connor, Bruce (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Dead Language Press, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Doyle, Kirby, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Fugs, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ginsberg, Allen, 1958-1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Johnson, Ray (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lamantia, Philip (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - LaVigne, Robert (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Malanga, Gerard (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - McClure, Michael, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Olsen, Charles, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Patchen, Kenneth, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Welch, Lew (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Whalen, Philip, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Wieners, John (Box 2, Folder 28)